Keith Marshall Collection of Photographs
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Keith Marshall collection of photographs
1880-1920
MSS 12
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
2
1 box, 1 oversize box
The collection comprises 147 photographs from the late 19th and early 20th centuries, with representative images of Great Britain, South Africa, New Zealand, Madeira, East Asia, and other locations (many unidentified).
Marshall, Keith
Caney, E. E.
Hana, George Henry, 1868-1838
Nicholls, Arthur, photographer
Rambert, Alex
Ravenscroft, Thomas Daniel, 1851-1950
Wilkinson, Scott, photographer
Williams, S. A. C.
Brown, Barnes & Bell
Martin and Sallnow (London, England)
Neue Photographische Gesellschaft
Pulman and Son Photographers
Sallo Epstein & Co.
Territorial Studio (Umtata, South Africa)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Keith (Yale BA 1968) and Millie Marshall, 2012
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: I. People; II. Places; III. Oversize.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises 147 photographs from the late 19th and early 20th centuries, with representative images of Great Britain, South Africa, New Zealand, Madeira, East Asia, and other locations (many unidentified). The various components of the collection were acquired by Keith Marshall during the course of his collecting of material on John Ruskin. The photographs were not, thus, assembled as an intentional (thematic) collection; they nonetheless provide an interesting selection of commercial, travel, and personal images of the late Victorian and early Edwardian periods.
The names of photographers are recorded on a number of the photographs. They include E.E. Caney, George Henry Hana, Arthur Nicholls, Alex Rambert, Thomas Daniel Ravenscroft, Scott Wilkinson, S.A.C. Williams, Brown Barnes & Bell, Martin and Sallnow, Pulman and Son Photographers, Sallo Epstein & Co., and the Territorial Studio (Umtata, South Africa).
The photographs are organized in topical groups, the most significant parts of which are as follows.
Maude Douglas: The collection includes a set of cabinet cards of the young actress, Maude Douglas, who performed, among other places, at the Theatre Royal, Drury Lane, in the 1890s. She was likely a dancer or other minor performer in burlesque theater. According to a partial inscription on one cabinet card, she appeared in an 1892 production of Faust up to date, a popular spoof of the legendary opera. These cards document theatrical costume and makeup of the fin de siècle, and evidence a young woman's perhaps fleeting career in show business. There is one letter and a calling card from Douglas as well. These items show that she also went by the name "Maude Francis" and married a Mr. Elliott.
Domestic interiors and exteriors: A significant part of the collection consists of photographs of interiors and exteriors of an affluent British or British-style home around the turn of the century, offering representative glimpses of interior decoration and domestic architecture of the period.
South Africa: The collection contains many images of various locations in South Africa, documenting the landscape and architecture of this area around the turn of the twentieth century. Locations represented include Cape Town and Durban.
Mariannhill Monastery: Among the oversize material are a set of album pages containing photos of Mariannhill, a Benedictine monastery that was founded in the 1880s, in Durban, South Africa. It was unusual for having its own photography and printing studio, and some of the images in this set seem to have come from this studio. The photos document the monks' daily lives and work, as well as missionary education in South Africa.
Mauritius: There are many images--most of them commercially produced, by Alex Rambert--of the island of Mauritius. These depict both landscapes and architectural scenes in and around the town of Reduit, in the 1880s or 1890s.
Venice: The collection includes a large set of commercially produced souvenir photographs of Venice (Italy), printed by the German company, Neue Photographische Gesellschaft (NPG). The NPG, an early example of a large-scale commercial photography business, established efficient and cost-effective printing processes and were an important part of European commercial photography in the 19th and 20th centuries.
Maori of New Zealand: There are a handful of large-scale portraits of Maori tribespeople and leaders. Identical images and negatives, matching some of the items in the present collection, are in the collection of the Museum of New Zealand.
Architecture, Domestic -- Great Britain; Country homes -- Great Britain; Interior decoration -- Great Britain; Maori (New Zealand people) -- Portraits; Missions -- South Africa; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Funchal (Madeira Islands) -- Pictorial works; Madeira Islands -- Pictorial works; Mauritius -- Pictorial works; South Africa -- Pictorial works; Swartberg Pass (South Africa) -- Pictorial works; Venice (Italy) -- Pictorial works; Albumen prints; Cabinet photographs; Interiors; Landscape photographs; Photographs; Portrait photographs; Travel photography; Douglas, Maude; Mariannhill (Monastery); Mariannhill Missionaries
- People, Series I
  - Maude Douglas
    - Maude Douglas calling card, 1892; 1 card; 6 x 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Calling card reading "Miss Maude Douglas, M. Van Biene's Companies, and Royal Opera House, Leicester." Dated in graphite, "Jany. 1892."
      Visiting cards; Douglas, Maude
    - Letter to "old Boysie", 1892 February; Douglas, Maude; 1 letter; 15 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Letter from Maude Douglas (signed "Maude Francis") dated Feb. 8 1892 (in graphite, perhaps at a later time), addressed to "old Boysie" and indicated as coming from "Theatre Royal/Drury Lane." Maude writes her friend to say that she is enclosing a photograph "as you desired" but that she has not been able to be photographed in her "Portugal dress" because "they cannot allow it until later on." She asks her correspondent to write and give her his/her opinion
      Correspondence
    - Maude Douglas portrait, bust-length profile, white dress, 1890s; Brown, Barnes & Bell; 1 albumen print; 16.5 x 10.8cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Portrait of Maude Douglas by Brown, Barnes, and Bell of Liverpool. Image shows Maude in profile, wearing a low-necked white dress or blouse that sits loosely on her shoulders. Her hair is pinned up in an informal way, not stiffly styled, and she has a fringe of curls framing her face. She wears no jewelry. Her lack of adornment, her naturalistic hairstyle and her soft neckline suggest that this photograph was taken perhaps as a performer's 'head-shot,' showcasing her natural features and beauty to greatest advantage.
      Cabinet photographs; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Portrait photographs; Albumen prints; Douglas, Maude
    - Maude Douglas portrait, full length seated, white dress, 1892; Brown, Barnes & Bell; 1 albumen print; 16.5 x 10.8 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
      This image and the profile image in the same group appear to have been taken at the same time, as part of a series. The print is dated "April 1892" in graphite on reverse. Maude is shown here in a loose and diaphanous white gown, with open sleeves that drape over her shoulders. Tassels adorn the dress at the arms and one at the waist. She wears no jewelry and her hair is done in a soft, natural, style.
      Albumen prints; Portrait photographs; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Cabinet photographs; Douglas, Maude
    - Maude Douglas portrait, checked blouse and pin, 1896; Hana, George Henry, 1868-1838; 1 photograph; 16.5 x 11cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Portrait of Maude Douglas is signed on reverse: "With Love from Maude/ D'cr [December] 9th 96." Image shows Maude looking straight at the camera, with curly bangs above her forehead. She wears a simple high-necked gingham or checked blouse, pinned at the neck with a small brooch.
      Photographs; Portrait photographs; Cabinet photographs; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Douglas, Maude
    - Maude Douglas portrait, bust length, wool coat, 1891; 1 albumen print; 16.5 x 10.8 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Signed on reverse, "Maude. Feb'y 1891." Image shows Maude looking straight at the camera, wearing a heavy coat and a feather-trimmed hat. She wears a brooch at her neck, but no other jewelry.
    - Maude Douglas portrait, full length, Greco-Roman gown, 1892; Williams, S. A. C.; 1 albumen print; 16.5 x 10.8 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Print is signed on back, "To Bertie with much love from Maudie." Image is of Maude standing with arms clasped behind her head. She wears a loosely-fitting, draped gown suggestive of ancient Greek or Roman style. She has a solid metallic bracelet on her right arm, and she wears heavy makeup.
      Albumen prints; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Cabinet photographs; Portrait photographs; Douglas, Maude
    - Maude Douglas portrait, full length seated, 'royal' costume, 1892; Williams, S. A. C.; 1 albumen print; 16.5 x 10.8 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Maude is shown here wearing a regal looking costume, consisting of a cap with pheasant feathers, a fur-trimmed striped bodice with dark fabric bib and cuffed sleeves (cuffs are a pale velvety material, with frilly wrists), a cape decorated with spangles, tasseled epaulets, thick black tights and low heeled black shoes. She is wearing heavy makeup, with her eyes lined and lips rouged. The print is signed, "With love from Maudie/ Jan 29th 92."
      Cabinet photographs; Portrait photographs; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Albumen prints; Douglas, Maude
    - Maude Douglas portrait, military costume, 1892 April; Brown, Barnes & Bell; 1 albumen print; 16.5 x 10.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Print is inscribed "April 1892" in graphite on reverse. Image shows Maude Douglas wearing a short military costume, consisting of a jacket embroidered with braid and piping and with wide lightweight cuffs, a sword slung across her body, a linked metallic belt with flags or some other military imagery stamped on each panel, a colorful sash, a cap, and gloves. Maude wears only thick pale-colored tights on her legs, with dark shiny boots that rise to mid-calf. She poses in a salute, with one hand on her sword.
      Cabinet photographs; Photographs; Albumen prints; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Douglas, Maude
    - Maude Douglas portrait, military costume, seated, 1892 April; Brown, Barnes & Bell; 1 albumen print; 16.5 x 10.8 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
      The second of two portraits taken of Maude in her short military costume. This image shows Maude seated on the wooden table that appears in the other portrait. She appears to hold a cigarette or some other small item in her right hand, between the first two fingers. Image is dated "April 1892" in graphite on reverse.
      Portraits; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Cabinet photographs; Albumen prints; Douglas, Maude
    - Maude Douglas portrait, military costume, hand-colored presentation copy, 1892 October 9; Brown, Barnes & Bell; 1 albumen print; 9 x 6.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Preserved in a slip of paper, in an envelope on which is written: "M.D. coloured herself/given me Sunday Oct. 9 1892/the week of her marriage to Mr. Elliott." This is a copy of the same print in which Maude appears saluting, in military costume. The print has been cut into a round-edged rectangle shape, perhaps for framing. On the reverse is part of an inscription from Maude, cut off when the print was resized: "Maude Douglas--'Faust up to [date]'." Faust up to date was a burlesque opera produced in the spring and summer of 1892.
      Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Portrait photographs; Albumen prints; Douglas, Maude
  - Portrait photographs of various sitters
    - Portrait of an older man, circa 1900; 1 albumen print; 13 x 8 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
      The sitter is unidentified. The back of the original picture frame is inscribed: "To Frankie, uncle. Jan. 31, 1842, Pa.; Jan. 31, 1913 Fla."
      Albumen prints; Portraits
    - Portrait of a young woman, with large hat, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 21 x 11 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Studio photograph of an unidentified sitter. The back of the frame has the printed label of Joseph Wilson, picture frame maker at London.
      Portrait photographs
    - Portrait of three young men, 1890s; Nicholls, Arthur (photographer); 1 albumen print; 16 x 11 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Portrait of three young men, all dressed in suits. They pose together on a couch, a chair, and a table in what appears to be the photographer's studio. There is no indication of the identity of the three men or the occasion of this portrait. This photograph was found with other photographs and envelopes bearing a Cambridge University (St. John's College) address, so it is possible that the three men are students at the University, possibly at St. John's College.
      Portrait photographs; Cabinet photographs; Albumen prints
    - Hetty Mitchell, 1899; Wilkinson, Scott (photographer); 1 photograph; 16.5 x 10.5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Photograph preserved in envelope which reads, on inside of the flap, "Hetty Mitchell. June 3, 1889." Presumably, this portrait depicts Hetty. It shows a young woman in her 20s or 30s, wearing a domestic servant's uniform.
      Photographs; Cabinet photographs; Portrait photographs; Mitchell, Hetty, 1890s
    - Portrait of an unidentified female performer, 1880s or 1890s; Martin and Sallnow (London, England); 1 albumen print; 16.5 x 11 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
      An unidentified female performer, likely from London, is pictured in this print. She stands with hands at her hips, wearing a revealing costume composed of a frilled eyelet blouse with long full sleeves, a vest and shorts of a pale color with dark edging, pale tights, and white shoes.
      Albumen prints; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Portrait photographs; Cabinet photographs
    - Family portrait, with small black dog, 1890s; 1 photograph; 17 x 22.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Family portrait of an unidentified man, woman, their five children, and a small dog. The family is arranged in the photographer's studio with mother and father seated at right and left, a young girl standing between them, and a small black dog on a pedestal in front. The family is dressed in what appear to be their best clothes, and the father wears a military jacket of some sort.
    - Portrait of mother and child, reading outdoors, circa 1900; 1 albumen print; 22.5 x 26.5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Print shows an unidentified mother and child in a garden setting. The mother, seated on an upholstered chair, is dressed in a pale or white gown with an embroidered square neck and a lace collar. She holds open a book and appears to be reading to a young girl standing next to her.
      Albumen prints; Portrait photographs
- Places, Series II
  - British domestic scenes
    - Unidentified interior, fireplace and armchairs, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15.5 x 20.5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph of an unidentified interior. One of a set of photographs showing interiors in a lavish home. Parquet wood flooring, oriental rugs, richly upholstered armchairs, a fireplace with carved/marble mantelpiece and floral screen, large sculptures, chandelier with crystal ornaments, and a large mirror with table underneath, containing various artifacts and decorative objects.
      Interior decoration -- Great Britain; Photographs
    - Unidentified interior, drawing room with curio cabinets and clock, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15.5 x 20.5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph of unidentified interior of a lavish home. Wooden side chairs and a large velvet armchair, many wall and table-top decorations, fresh flowers, an ornate wall clock, and a large curio cabinet with glass windows on front/sides. China and crystal displayed in the cabinet. Chandelier with crystal ornaments, oriental rugs on parquet wood floor.
      Photographs; Upholstery -- Great Britain; Interior decoration -- Great Britain
    - Unidentified interior, dining or breakfast room, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15.5 x 20.5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph of unidentified dining room. A small round table is set with fine china and cloth napkins. Leather dining chairs surround table and are placed against wall. An ornate and robust wooden cabinet is at the back of the room. The cabinet has carved decorations on the front and wooden figures at top. A silver tea or coffee service is in the back corner of the scene. A large oriental rug covers the floor.
    - Unidentified interior, dining room, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15 x 20.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph of unidentified dining room, with a table setting for four. A tapestry and scrollwork fire screen is set in front of the fireplace, and several glass jars are set atop the mantel, in front of a mirror. The room has dark wood paneling on all walls. The chairs are upholstered in studded leather. A large woven rug is on the floor, and a sidebar with silver atop it is seen in the background. Electric sconces, each with a single bulb, are located on the walls.
      Upholstery -- Great Britain; Interior decoration -- Great Britain; Photographs
    - Unidentified interior, living room or library, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15.5 x 20.5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph of an unidentified living room. Two painted portraits are shown--a large one of three boys hangs over the fireplace (with elaborately carved mantel); a second depicts a woman in a low-necked dress. Various wall and free standing decorations, ornaments, throughout the room. A couch is covered in a patterned velvet textile, and several chairs appear grouped around an orientalist carved table.
      Upholstery -- Great Britain; Photographs; Interior decoration -- Great Britain
    - Unidentified interior, sitting room, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15 x 20.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph depicting an elaborately decorated sitting room. In the foreground, a couch appears with lace covered pillows and a vibrant floral upholstery. Two rugs can be seen on the floor, both large and also striking in appearance. A wooden rocking chair with additional cushions sits at left, with a closed hutch behind it. Books and photographs are housed in a shelving unit with a fabric skirt, in the background. The photographs depict various people and are likely family or friends' portraits.
    - Unidentified interior, living room or library, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15 x 20.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph of unidentified living room or library in this series. A table is draped with a fringed covering, and large books or albums stacked in three groups atop it. Bookshelves with fine leather-bound volumes are visible in the background at left. A large stand or easel is also at left, in carved wood, with a portfolio resting on top of it. There is a heavy wooden desk with an unusual carved chair in front of it. The desk has a large lamp and other decorative items atop it. In the background, a long upholstered couch is built along the back wall. Framed images and some sculptural wall art are hung above it. There are armchairs and other lounging chairs at right, with the same tasseled-textile coverings as appear in the other photo of this room. A large sculpture of a muscular, bearded, man with a lion resting at his feet (perhaps Androcles and the lion?), stands at right on a pedestal.
      Photographs; Interior decoration -- Great Britain; Upholstery -- Great Britain
    - Unidentified interior, staircase and hall, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15 x 20.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph depicts a dark wooden staircase that rises from left bottom to right top, with a long landing or balcony at right. Below the stairs is an open sitting area, presumably in the first floor main hall.
      Photographs; Interior decoration -- Great Britain
    - Unidentified home, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15 x 20.5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Unidentified stately brick home with glass walled conservatory at back.
      Photographs
    - Unidentified estate or hotel, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 16.5 x 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Depicts an unknown property on a waterfront. Large brick or stone building with a conservatory and several turrets. A flag (Australian?) flies at the top of the tallest turret. A steamboat can be seen in the water at right, in the distance.
      Albumen prints
    - Unidentified family group at home, 1900s; 1 photograph; 15 x 20.5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Unidentified family group arranged casually on steps and front wall of a two story home with two chimneys and detailed trim. The home looks to be a modern one for its era, with long glass windows (a couple are opened on their hinges). There is a gravel drive and a landscaped garden with trees and rosebushes in the foreground.
    - Unidentified home and garden, exterior view, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15 x 20.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph shows a half-timbered house with decorative Victorian-era design elements. Ivy grows thickly on the first floor of the house, which is shown from the side. A graveled drive runs to its right, and a small garden is shown in the foreground. There is another home in the background, at right, in this photograph.
      Architecture, Domestic; Photographs
    - Unidentified home, exterior view, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 15 x 21.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph of an unidentified, large half-timbered home, pictured likely around the turn of the twentieth century. No people appear in the image. The home appears at the base of an extensive graveled drive, with bushes and trees growing at the edges.
      Photographs; Architecture, Domestic; Country homes -- Great Britain
    - Unidentified group in early automobile, 1910s; 1 photograph; 12 x 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph depicting unidentified group of people (3 women, a man, and a male driver) with a parked car. Several pieces of luggage arranged on the running board. The women all wear head coverings (hats and veils) and a sole woman is standing by the car in a long duster coat. The driver wears a uniform. The car and clothing indicate that the image dates from the early 1900s or 1910s.
      Automobiles; Photographs
    - Unidentified women with automobile, 1910s or 1920s; 1 photograph; 24 x 18 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photograph depicting unidentified trio of women with a car. Automobile appears early, but not of earliest design, so likely dates to 1910s or 1920s. The car is parked on a dirt road or path that is wooded on either side. Two women sit in the car, with the youngest woman at the wheel and an older woman next to her. A third woman poses jauntily with her foot on the running board. Her dress, shoes, wristwatch, and hairstyle seem to date this photograph to ca. 1915-1925. There is no information in or with the photograph, but it was found with a group of photos depicting scenes (exterior and interior) of a large home.
      Photographs; Automobiles
    - Unidentified road, circa 1900; 1 photograph; 21 x 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Depicts a landscaped road or driveway with trees and brush growing on banks at either side. No indication of location but found grouped with other images of interiors and domestic scenes.
  - Mauritius
    - Unidentified rock pillar, Mauritius (?), 1880s or 1890s; Rambert, Alex; 1 photograph; 22 x 16 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Has the ink stamp of "Alex. Rambert" on the reverse. Depicts a naturally-formed pillar of rocks, with some plants growing at the base. A man stands near the foot of the pillar.
      Mauritius; Photographs